<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="info" ipr="full3978" docName="openid-ui-1_0.xml">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc private="Implementers' Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="OpenID UI 1.0">OpenID User Interface Extension 1.0 - DRAFT 0.4</title>

    <author initials="A" surname="Tom" fullname="Allen Tom">
      <organization>Yahoo!</organization>
      <address>
        <email>atom@yahoo-inc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="B" surname="de Medeiros" fullname="Breno de Medeiros">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>breno@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="May" year="2009"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	This specification defines a mechanism to support OpenID user interfaces 
	optimized for different environments and languages.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
    <section anchor="conv" title="Notation and Conventions">
          <t>The keywords MUST, MUST NOT, REQUIRED, SHALL, 
	    SHALL NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT, RECOMMENDED, MAY, 
	    and OPTIONAL in this document are to be interpreted as 
	    described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>. 
           </t>
	  <t>
            Unless otherwise noted, this specification is written as a direct
            continuation of <xref target="OpenID 2.0" />, inheriting the definitions and
            guidelines set by it.
	  </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Overview">
      <t>
	OpenID traditionally required the Relying Party to redirect the entire browser 
	window to the OpenID Provider for the user to authenticate before redirecting 
	the browser back to the Relying Party. It is believed that the User Experience (UX) 
	could be significantly improved if the authentication flow occurred within a separate
	popup window, making the experience less disruptive to the user. 
      </t>
      <t>
	Although it is possible for Relying Parties to open a popup window for the user to
	authenticate at	the OpenID Provider using the Provider's default user interface, 
	the overall user experience can be optimized if the OP was aware that its UI was running 
	within a popup. For instance, an OP may want to resize the popup browser window when using
	the popup interface, but would probably not want to resize the full browser 
	window when using the default redirect interface.
	Another optimization is that the OP can close the popup, rather than 
	return a negative assertion if the user chooses to cancel the authentication request.
      </t>
      <t>
	This extension also adds support for Relying Parties to indicate the user's language
	preference to the OP, potentially making the transition from the RP to the OP less disruptive
	to the user.
	</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Extension Namespace">
	  <t>
	    All OpenID 2.0 messages that contain a UI Extension element MUST 
	    contain the following extension namespace declaration, as specified in the 
	    Extensions section of <xref target="OpenID 2.0"/>.
	    </t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork>
 openid.ns.&lt;alias&gt;=http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>
	  The actual extension namespace alias should be determined on a per-message basis
	  by the party composing the messages, in such a manner as to avoid conflicts between 
	  multiple extensions. For the purposes of this document, the extension namespace used
	  for all examples is "ui". 
	</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Language Preference">
      <t>
	When requesting OpenID authentication using the checkid_setup mode, the Relying Party MAY send the 
	OP a hint regarding the user's preferred language by sending the following parameters:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="hanging"> 
	  <t hangText="openid.ns.ui">
	    REQUIRED. Value: "http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0"
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="openid.ui.lang">
	    REQUIRED. The user's preferred languages as a <xref target="BCP 47" /> language priority list, 
	    represented as a comma-separated list of BCP 47 basic language ranges in descending priority order. 
	    For instance, the value "fr-CA,fr-FR,en-CA" represents the preference for French spoken in Canada, 
	    French spoken in France, followed by English spoken in Canada. 
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      
      <t>
	The language preference hint SHOULD take precedence over the Accept-Language
	HTTP header sent by the user's browser, and SHOULD take precedence over the language 
	preference inferred by the user's IP address. 
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Requesting Authentication in a Popup">
      <t>
	The Relying Party SHOULD first request authentication using the checkid_immedidate mode if the Relying Party 
	has reason to believe that user had previously authenticated at the Relying Party and can determine
	the user's OpenID Provider.
      </t>
      <t>
	When requesting OpenID authentication using the checkid_setup mode, the Relying Party MUST send
	the following parameters:
      </t>
      <t>
	  <list style="hanging"> 
	    <t hangText="openid.ns.ui">
	      REQUIRED. Value: "http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0"
	    </t>
	    <t hangText="openid.ui.mode">
	      REQUIRED. Value: "popup".
	      New modes may be defined in future versions of this extension.
	    </t>
	  </list>
      </t>
      <t>
	The RP SHOULD create the popup to be 450 pixels wide and 500 pixels tall. 
	The popup MUST have the address bar displayed, and MUST be in a standalone browser
	window. The contents of the popup MUST NOT be framed by the RP. 
      </t>
      <t>
	The RP SHOULD open the popup centered above the main browser window, and SHOULD dim
	the contents of the parent window while the popup is active. The RP SHOULD ensure 
	that the user is not surprised by the appearance of the popup, and understands
	how to interact with it.
	
      </t>
      <t>
	To keep the user popup user experience consistent, it is RECOMMENDED that
	the OP does not resize the popup window unless the OP requires additional 
	space to show special features that are not usually displayed as part of the 
	default popup user experience.
      </t>
      <t>
	The OP MAY close the popup without returning a response to the RP. 
	Closing the popup without sending a response should be interpreted as a 
	negative assertion.
      </t>
      <t>
      The response to an authentication request in a popup is unchanged from 
      <xref target="OpenID 2.0" />.
      Relying Parties detecting that the popup was closed without receiving an authentication response
      SHOULD interpret the close event to be a negative assertion.
      </t>

      <section title="Authentication Response in a Fragment">
	<t>
	  The user experience can be optimized by returning the authentication response parameters in 
	  the fragment portion of the Relying Party's return_to URL, allowing the content of the return_to 
	  URL to be returned from the browser's cache, if already present.  To use this 
	  technique, the Relying Party MUST include the fragment delimiter (the "#" character) in the return_to 
	  URL in the authentication request. If the fragment delimiter character is present in the return_to URL, 
	  the OpenID Provider SHOULD return the response parameters in the fragment portion of the URL. If the
	  return_to URL already contains a question mark "?", the first response parameter MUST be prefixed 
	  with an ampersand "&", otherwise the first response parameter MUST be prefixed with a question mark "?".
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Discovery">
	<t>
	  OpenID Providers supporting the User Interface Extension SHOULD advertise their support of the
	  Extension using OpenID Discovery as defined in Section 7.3 of <xref target="OpenID 2.0" />.
	</t>
	<t>
	  OpenID Providers supporting the language preference functionality SHOULD define
	  http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0/lang-pref as a &lt;xrd:Type&gt; child element of the &lt;xrd:Service&gt; element 
	  in the XRDS discovery document.
	</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
&lt;Type&gt;http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0/lang-pref&lt;/Type&gt;
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>
	  OpenID Providers supporting the popup functionality SHOULD define
	  http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0/mode/popup as a  &lt;xrd:Type&gt; child element 
	  of the &lt;xrd:Service&gt; element in the 
	  XRDS discovery document.
	</t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork>
&lt;Type&gt;http://specs.openid.net/extensions/ui/1.0/mode/popup&lt;/Type&gt;
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

      </section>
    <section title="Considerations">
      <t>
	OpenID Providers SHOULD use HTTPS for all their authentication screens, and educate
	their users to always check their browser's address bar before entering their 
	credentials. OPs SHOULD implement Javascript framebusting code to prevent their UI from
	being framed.
      </t>
      <t>
	Credential verification and approval screens SHOULD always be in an independent browser
	window to protect the user's credentials and approval from clickjacking exploits.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	Allen Tom (atom@yahoo-inc.com)
      </t>
      <t>
	Breno de Medeiros (breno@google.com)
      </t>
      <t>
	Brian Ellin (brian@janrain.com)
      </t>
      <t>
	Chris Messina (chris@citizenagency.com)
      </t>
      <t>
	David Recordon (david@sixapart.com)
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>
    
  <back>
    <references title="References">

      <reference anchor="BCP 47">
	<front>
          <title>Tags for Identifying Languages</title>
          <author initials="A.P." surname="Phillips" fullname="Addison Phillips">
	    <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M.D." surname="Davis" fullname="Mark Davis">
	    <organization>Google</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="47" />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="OpenID 2.0">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID 2.0</title>
          <author initials="" surname="OpenID 2.0 Workgroup" fullname="OpenID 2.0 Core Workgroup">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://openid.net" />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="OpenID Attribute Exchange">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Attribute Exchange 1.0</title>

          <author initials="D.H." surname="Hardt" fullname="Dick Hardt">
            <organization>Sxip Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J.B." surname="Bufu" fullname="Johnny Bufu">
            <organization>Sxip Identity</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J.H." surname="Hoyt" fullname="Josh Hoyt">
            <organization>JanRain</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-attribute-exchange-1_0.html" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Language Preference Attribute">
        <front>
          <title>Language Preference Attribute</title>
          <author initials="" surname="axschema.org" fullname="axschema.org">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://axschema.org/pref/language" />
      </reference>




      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials="B.S" surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
